University of Arizona Association for Women Faculty Records, 1970-2008 (bulk 1981-2008)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
University of Arizona Association for Women Faculty Records 1970-2008 1981-2008
MS 334
Unviersity of Arizona. Association for Women Faculty
This collection contains materials relating to the University of Arizona Association for Women Faculty (AWF). Collection also consists of materials relating to the UA AWF’s predecessor, the Committee on the Status of University Women, and previous women’s advocacy organizers on campus. The bulk of the collection is administrative materials and correspondence pertaining to AWF committee coordination.
7 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None
Further accurals are anticipated
Biographical Note
Association for Women Faculty (AWF) was founded in 1981 due to an identified need to advocate for women faculty and academic professionals at the University of Arizona. Prior to the AWF, women’s organizational groups on campus advocated for women faculty, administrators, staff, and students under the auspices of the Committee on the Status of University Women (CSUW). As the AWF’s predecessor this group helped usher in the establishment of a Women Studies program at the University of Arizona and was proactive in the elimination of sexist language on UA documents. However, due to the wide academic population that the CSUW served, women faculty and academic professionals reorganized into the Association for Women Faculty. From 1982-1984, the AWF spearheaded a campaign to rectify salary inequity at the university (which resulted in a total of $200,000 in salary adjustment). In subsequent years, the AWF prioritized monitoring salary equity and worked along with the administration to ensure that equitable and adequate policies are sponsored and implemented to improve the quality of life for all UA women.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into nine series
Series I: Administrative, 1970-1972, 1981-2008 1970-1972, 1981-2008
Series II: Financial Records, 1986-2004 1986-2004
Series III: Committees, 1971-2006 1971-2006
Series IV: Membership, 1984-2006 1984-2006
Series V: Correspondence, 1982-2007 1982-2007
Series VI: Publications, 1973-2007 1973-2007
Series VII: Reports, 1983-2003 1983-2003
Series VIII: Ephemera
Series IX: Floppy Disks
Scope and Content Note
This collection spans from 1970-2008. The bulk of material relates to the Association for Women Faculty. However, some material prior to the establishment of the Association of Women Faculty in 1982 is included. These early materials are: the records of Dr. Shirley Fahey and her activities in advocating for women on campus at the University of Arizona and the subsequent establishment of the Committee on the Status of University Women thereafter.
Access Terms
Fahey, Shirley
Arizona Board of Regents. Commission on the Status of Women
University of Arizona- Faculty
Equal pay for equal work-Arizona-Tucson
Pay equity- Arizona
Sex discrimination against women- Arizona- Tucson
Sex discrimination in employment- Arizona- Tucson
Universities and colleges- Employees- Arizona
Universities and colleges- Arizona- Faculty
Wages- Women
Women college teachers- Arizona
Women- Arizona- Tucson- Societies and clubs
Associations, institutions, etc.- Arizona- Tucson
Women’s rights- Arizona
Container List
- Series I: Administrative, 1970-1972, 1981-2008
  Series is sorted by year. This series contains the constitution and bylaws of the AWF and subsequent revisions to it, committee minutes, agendas, handwritten notes, some correspondence that pertains to AWF executive committee and officer coordination, speech notes, and statistics. Some years have supplemental material attached regarding planning or other committee activity. Surveys are also included as administrative tools. Important to note that early activity pertaining to women’s advocacy, prior to the CSUW, are also included in this series. Series is sorted by year. This series contains the constitution and bylaws of the AWF and subsequent revisions to it, committee minutes, agendas, handwritten notes, some correspondence that pertains to AWF executive committee and officer coordination, speech notes, and statistics. Some years have supplemental material attached regarding planning or other committee activity. Surveys are also included as administrative tools. Important to note that early activity pertaining to women’s advocacy, prior to the CSUW, are also included in this series.
  - Early Organizers for Women, Records of Dr. Shirley Fahey, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Consitution and Bylaws (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Surveys, 1984-2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Womens Advisory Council to the President, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Planning "Women and Minorities" with Cecilia Preciado Burciaga, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Planning "Sustaining Faculty Diversity in the Research University", 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - AWF Search for Vice President of Affirmative Action, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Survey of Professional Women at UA, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Survey of Professional Women at UA, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Planning "Life Without Affirmative Action" Event, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - AWF History Project, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1999 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 2000 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 2001 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - AWF Elections, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 2002 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - University of Arizona Conference on Subtle Discrimination, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Women to Women Reception, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 2004 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - AWF Graduate Research Symposium, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 2006 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - AWF Speech at University of ARizona Presidential Inaugural, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 2008 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Series II: Financial Records, 1986-2004 1986-2004
  Series is broken up into two types: financial records and grants. Series is further sorted by year and alphabetized by subject. Materials include receipts pertaining to travel arrangements, AWF banking statements, rental agreements, and treasury reports.
  - 1989-1992 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1995-1997 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 2001-2006 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Grants, AWF Travel Grant, 1992-1995 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Grants, AWF Travel Grant Genderal Guidelines (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Grants, Bryn Mawr Summer Institute for Women in Higher Education Fellowship, 1986-1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Grants, Commission on the Status of Women, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series III: Committees, 1971-2006 1971-2006
  Series is sorted alphabetically by committee name, then by year. Committee files contain correspondence, meeting minutes, handwritten notes, and reference materials that these committees used. Series mainly contains AWF committees, but other external committees in which the AWF was involved are included such as the Arizona Board of Regents’ Commission on the Status of Women. The Committee on Status of University Women (CSUW) are also included; it is important to note that these CSUW files are pre-AWF.
  - Academic Professionals, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Academic Professional, 2000-2002 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Action, 1987-1994 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Action, 1996-1999 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Arizona Board of Regents Commission on the Status of Women, 1988-1990 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Arizona Board of Regents Commissionon the Status of Women, 1991-1994 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Arizona Board of Regents Commission on the Status of Women, 1997-2000 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Family Care, 1993-1999 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Family Care, Child Care Program Examples (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Graduate and Professional Students, Graduate Symposium Submissions, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Graduate and Professional Student, Graduate Symposium, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Graduate and Professional Students, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Liaison to ASU-NAU, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Parental, Leave Policies, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Parental, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Parental, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Parental Concerns, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Parental Concerns, Committee Reference Publications (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Planning, 1981-1984 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Professional Development, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Professional Womens Concerns, 1986-1988 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Salary Equity Review, 1982-2006 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Salary Equity Review, Salary Evaluation Kit (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Salary Equity Review, History of Salary Equity, 1982-1984 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Settling-in and Lifestyle, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Status, 1982-1985, 1992-1993 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Status of University Women CSUW Records, Administrative, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Status of University Women CSUW Records, Administrative, Original proposal for creating Women Studies Program at UA, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Status of University Women CSUW REcords, Administrative, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Status of University Women CSUW Records, Administrative, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Status of University Women CSUW Records, Administrative, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Status of University Women CSUW Records, Administrative, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Status of University Women CSUW Records, Correspondence, 1972-1981 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Status of University Women CSUW Records, Membership Mail, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Status of University Women CSUW Records, Affirmative Action, 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Status of University Women CSUW Records, Task Forces, 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Status of University Women CSUW Records, Publications, Newsletters, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Status of University Women CSUW Records, Publications, Newspaper Clippings, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Status of University Women CSUW Records, Statistics, 1971-1976 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Status of University Women CSUW Records, Constitution and Bylaws (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Membership, 1984-2006 1984-2006
  Series is sorted by type, then by year. Types are: List and Forms. Lists pertain to membership lists that were compiled to include contact information of each member, furthermore, lists is also divided to reflect an Arizona Board of Regents Luncheon coordination effort made by the treasurer. Forms pertain to membership submissions and membership fees.
  - List, AWF, 1983-1987 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - List, AWF, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - List, AWF, 1990-2006 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - List, Arizona Board of Regents Luncheon, 1992-2001 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Forms, 1990-1996 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Forms, 2000-2004 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Series V: Correspondence, 1982-2007 1982-2007
  Series is sorted by type, then by year. Correspondence types are: general correspondence, correspondence with the Office of the President, correspondence with the Office of the Provost and Vice Provost of Academic Affairs, correspondence with the Office of Vice President for Affirmative Action, and correspondence of Membership. Some photographs are included within series.
  - General Correspondence, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Holiday Reception Photographs, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - General Correspondence, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - General Correspondence, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with Office of the President, 1983-1993 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with Office of the President, 1998-2007 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with Office of the Provost and Vice Provost of Academic Affairs, 1983-1985 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence with Office of the Provost and Vice Provost of Academic Affairs, 1986-1989 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Office of the Provost and Vice Provost of Academic Affairs, 1990-1993 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Office of the Provost and Vice Provost of Academic Affairs, 1994-2001 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Office of Assistant Vice President for Affirmative Action, 1983-1988 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence of Membership, 1983-2001 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Series VI: Publications, 1973-2007 1973-2007
  Series is sorted by type, then by year. Types are: AWF Publications, Reference Materials, Newspaper Clippings, and Oversize Publications. AWF Publications consist largely of the monthly newsletters this organizations had distributed in order to keep up to speed the members of the AWF on committee activities. Reference materials pertains to external publications that were implemented by the AWF. Newspaper Clippings consist mainly of the salary equity issues that were publicized by the local or campus press. Oversize publications materials consist publications are all inclusive of the before mentioned types.
  - AWF Publications, Newsletters, 1983-1989 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - AWF Publications, Newsletters, 1990-1994 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - AWF Publications, Newsletters, 1995-1999 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - AWF Publications, Newsletters, 2000-2007 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - AWF Publications, Proceedings of the Graduate Symposium, 2004 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Reference Materials, University Resources, Arizona State University (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Reference Materials, University Resources, UC Irvine, UC Berkeley, UC San Francisco (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Reference Materials, University Resources, University of Nevada Reno, University of Michigan, University of Minnesota (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Reference Materials, Essays and Articles, Parental (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Reference Materials, Essays and Articles, Retention (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Reference Materials, Essays and Articles, Retention (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Reference Materials, Essays and Articles, Salary Equity (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Reference Materials, Essays and Articles, Sex Equity and Professionalism (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Salary Equity, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Salary Equity, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1986-1998 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Oversize Publications, 1973-2003 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Oversize Publications, UA Salary Analysis by Gender, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Series VII: Reports, 1983-2003 1983-2003
  Series is sort by year and then alphabetized. Includes reports in which the AWF contributed to in some capacity.
  - Faculty Salaries by Gender Summary Report, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - AWF Report from the Working Party, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - AFfirmative Action Plan, 1984-1987 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - "Hiring and Retaining Women Faculty" by Kathryn Moore, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Survey used by Kathryn Moore for AWF Survey, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1988-1989 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - The "Invisible Minority" by Karen Anderson, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1991 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Plan of Implementation: Arizona Board of regents' Commission on the Status of Women; Reaching the Vision: Women in Arizona's Universities in the Year 2000, 1991; 1991 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Arizona Board of Regents Commission on the Status of Women Annual Report, 1992-1993 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - UA Consolidated Employee Diversity Progress Report, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Arizona Board of Regents Commissionon the Status of Women Annual Report, 1993-1994 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Arizona Board of Regents Commission on the Status of Women, 1998 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - "Challenging the Bias" by Roberta Moore, 1998 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - The Millenium Project Summary Report, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - The Millennium Project Report in Detail, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - The Millennium Project Phase Two, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Student Campus Climate Assessment and Tracking Study; Graduate Study Dependent and Child Care Study, 2001;2003 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Series VIII: Ephemera
  Series consists mainly of AWF brochures that describe organization agendas by academic year.
  - AWF Brochures, 1987-2004 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - AWF Letterhead (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - AWF Membership Sign-up Sign (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Flyers (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Series IX: Floppy Disks
  Floppy disks have not been transferred to new media
  - Maureen Kelly’s AWF Disk (1) 3 ½” Floppy Diskette (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Financial Records Disk, 1991-1992 (1) 5 ¼” Floppy Disk (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - AWF Member, Ledger, Deposit Disk (1) 5 ¼” Floppy Disk (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - AWF Brochure Disk (1) 5 ¼” Floppy Disk (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - AWF Logo Disks, 1998 (3) 3 ½” Floppy Diskette (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - AWF List- Hymel, 2001 (1) 3 ½” Floppy Diskette (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - AWF 2001 (1) 3 ½” Floppy Diskette (Box 16, Folder 9)